בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is דף ג׳. Daf Gimmel.
We pick up on the bottom of ב׳ עמוד ב׳, Bet Amud
Bet, we're in the middle of a very important discussion about which
is on the left for a little bit, whether, I mean on
and off, which is this discussion about היזק ראיה שמי היזק. Hezek
Re'iyah Shemei Hezek. If you're looking into somebody else's private affairs that
they're doing in their house, in their yard, etc., it's considered a
form of damaging them, which would then presumably obligate you to prevent
it from happening and to build a wall.
And it's sort of tied into a textual question of the משנה,
Mishnah, whether to read the משנה Mishnah that as soon as they
agree to divide the yard there's an obligation to build a wall,
or the more פשט Pshat of the משנה Mishnah that if they
agree to build the wall they have to build the wall, but
there's no obligation to build a wall. So there was that two
readings. Certainly the פשט Pshat reading was the latter, but then later
in the משנה Mishnah it seemed very clear that at least in
the case of a גינה Ginah you have to build a wall.
And sort of intuitively we would assume that a garden there's less
a concern of invasion of privacy, but the גמרא Gemara has an
אוקימתא Okimta that maybe there's more of a concern in a garden
because of the idea of like עין הרע. Ayin hara. You damage
a person more. So that still is a open question. And the
last point we left off with was a later משנה Mishnah that
says that if there was a wall and it fell down, then
you can't force the other person to rebuild it. Why is that?
רש"י Rashi makes it sound like, well there was already some contractual
implicit agreement to build it so that you have to then continue
keeping it built, like sort of a fulfillment of the earlier agreement.
But תוספות Tosafot importantly makes it part of this היזק ראיה Hezek
Re'iyah discussion. And תוספות Tosafot says no, in that case once you
have gotten to be accustomed to doing private, you know,
activities in your yard, it is a היזק ראיה Hezek Re'iyah now
if the person can look into it. So it seems like what
we're really dealing with is like both in this case of גינה
Ginah and this case of תוספות Tosafot and other cases, like nobody
debates the idea that there are forms of invading somebody's privacy that
is considered היזק. Hezek. The question is like how broad or narrow
is that scope? Okay, so according to תוספות Tosafot if I already
had that right, if I already had that freedom and now you're
invading it, that would be היזק. Hezek. So let's continue now in
the גמרא Gemara as it continues to try to prove this. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא שמע. Tashma.
It's about twenty lines from the bottom, line starts with אותו Oto
and it's תא שמע Tashma with a little like hey in half,
and a half brackets. תא שמע. Tashma. כופין אותו לבנות בית שער
ודלת לחצר. Kofinoso livnot beit sha'ar vedelet lechatzer.
So there's another coming up משנה. Mishnah. You can force somebody, now
the somebody here is a fellow member of your courtyard. Okay, so
this is not that two people share a yard, but a group
of houses share a yard, the standard arrangement for those that remember
from עירובין Eiruvin is that you would have multiple houses opening up
into, okay these are your houses, opening up into a חצר. Chatzer.
This would be your yard, these would be your houses. And then
the חצר Chatzer could open up into like a מבוי, Mavoy, an
alley, and maybe or maybe even a רשות הרבים. Reshut harabim. Okay,
or maybe the מבוי Mavoy open up into a רשות הרבים. Reshut
harabim. Okay, anyway but you have your individual houses opening up into
the courtyard. So if you have a courtyard here and there's a
gate around the courtyard, right, and you have to go through that
gate to get into the courtyard, okay, and you want to build
a בית שער, Beit sha'ar, a like a gatehouse. Thank you. Okay,
and what that gatehouse is going to do is it will also
prevent the people who are going on the street from, we're going
to call it רשות הרבים Reshut harabim now, it could be more
of an alleyway. But anyway, from looking into your courtyard. Okay, so
you are protecting, that's true, but the immediate concern here at least
from the גמרא's Gemara perspective is the looking in. So the concern
here is, it's actually an interesting case. It's not totally private activity
because you're going to be doing it in a courtyard that you
share with other houses, okay, but you want to prevent people from
watching what you do in this shared courthouse, not totally private activity.
And you are, and the question is who are you forcing to
build this gatehouse? You're not going to force the people of רשות
הרבים, Reshut harabim, the people that are doing the damage through their
looking. You're going to force your fellow members of the courtyard. Everybody
has to chip in in order to build this courthouse, this gatehouse.
So you're forcing each other to protect yourselves collectively from the היזק
ראיה Hezek Re'iyah of רשות הרבים. Reshut harabim. That's the case. So
let's read this. Okay, מחייבין אותו, Makhayivinoso, כופין אותו Kofinoso excuse me
לבנות בית שער ודלת לחצר. Livnot beit sha'ar vedelet lechatzer. And presumably
the reason is as Michael says maybe it's to protect them, but
the גמרא Gemara here assumes it's to protect them not from like
actual physical invasion but from the visual invasion. So תא שמע Tashma
שמע מינה היזק ראיה שמי היזק. shma mina hezek re'iyah shemei hezek.
The fact that I can force my fellow courtyard member to do
it shows that this is considered a damage that is occurring to
the courtyard. Now by the way notice that this is important again,
I know I keep on going back to this, about why it's
important to frame this in the גמרא's Gemara terms or the consequences
of framing it in the גמרא's Gemara terms rather than in our
Western terms. If you call this a right to privacy, so we
all have a right to privacy, יישר כח, Shkoyach, why does it
mean I can force everybody to chip in for that? Right? Why
just because we have a right to privacy, right? But if it's
no, there's this thing called damage that's being done when other people
look into us. So now our courtyard is being damaged, as it
were, we're being injured, we're being damaged, then everybody in the courtyard
can be sort of forced one another to protect ourselves collectively from
this damage. So the same way we can force ourselves to build
a wall around it to keep it safe, we can force the
other members to keep it safe from this היזק ראיה. hezek re'iyah.
So by framing it as
היזק, hezek, that means not just that you can force the people
doing that היזק, hezek, how are you going to force רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim to build it? But you can force each other to
protect ourselves collectively from this damage. Okay, and that's why it learns
from this, you know, it derives from this that היזק ראיה שמי
היזק. Hezek re'iyah shemei hezek. Yes, go ahead. I want to push
you on that because the fact that you have a right to
privacy or a right or that the goal is to avoid היזק
hezek does not necessarily tell you what other rights go along with
it. Meaning, you can have a right to privacy and in some
particular place that right to privacy includes the right to force other
people to enable you to be private. I mean I don't. Okay,
alright, so I'm glad that there's a lawyer here to keep me
honest, because I'm just thinking like conceptually, you know conceptually to me
it means. Right, right, the right could. Right. So you're saying you
could have, so I appreciate that. So you're saying you in theory
could have a legal system where it's called a right to privacy
and I can actually to protect that right enforce somebody who's not
invading that right, right, but somebody who will, I need their help
to help me protect that right, I can sort of force them
to to do this. Right, and for example in. You don't need
their help, you can skip over. Well, whatever, but in an apartment
building, right, in an apartment building there's a, you know, there's a,
you have a contract among all the people in the, and so
if the board says that you have to, you know, build a
court, build a. Yes, but that's because of virtue of the contract.
The point here is there is no contract, the only thing that's
allowing me to force somebody is the presence of the היזק ראיה.
hezek re'iyah. So okay, but okay, I hear your point that you
know it's always a question of how do you define the implications
of that thing that we're talking about. But I do, but but
let's just focus, or I don't want to constantly be making that
argument, but I do want to say that because it's defining it
as היזק, hezek, that allows the גמרא Gemara within that concept to
say oh, well you know, if you're being physically damaged, you can
force everybody to make a wall to protect yourselves against robbers and
physical damage, you can protect, everybody to make a wall against this
type of damage as well. And this is very interesting, so the
gate is in the בית שער beis sha'ar and such that the
בית שער beis sha'ar is preventing people from seeing in. Yeah, not
exactly, רש"י Rashi sort of says it's like you have a gate,
exactly, you have a gate house like this and there's a little
door here and a little door there that gets you out and
the guy stands in there somehow that that actually physically blocks the
view. Okay. The גמרא Gemara can say like, alright, you know what,
this gate house is expensive, let's just put like, you know, some
trans, you know. Okay, I don't know, there's also the word דלת
deles here, so maybe, yeah. Anyway, תא שמע, tash, so the גמרא
Gemara says, שמע מינה Shema mina היזק ראיה שמי היזק. hezek re'iyah
shemei hezek. If you can force each other, that must be because
of this damage that's occurring to the members of the courtyard. So
it says, no, היזקא דרבים שאני. hezeka derabbim shani. So again, multiple
ways the גמרא Gemara is not debating the principle. It's just debating
the scope. Damage caused by every walker by being able to look
in is a different type of היזק hezek than by my next
door neighbor having that ability. Okay? Which means that then there it
is היזק hezek and you can force. No, no, we're not denying
the משנה. mishnah. No, but if it was just two people, not
necessarily, exactly. So we're not debating the principle, we're debating the scope.
Okay. היזקא דרבים שאני. hezeka derabbim shani. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ויחיד לא, veyachid lo, but an individual not? תא שמע tashma come
and hear. אין חולקין את החצר עד שיהא בו ארבע אמות לזה
וארבע אמות לזה. ein chokin es hachatzer ad sheyehei bo arba amos
leze ve'arba amos leze. You do not divide a courtyard until there
be in it ארבע אמות arba amos for this one and ארבע
אמות arba amos for that one. You can't force somebody if we
share a yard, I can't force you to split it, you don't
want to split it, you want to keep it shared. So if
we each can get out of the split a four-by-four אמות amos
yard, then I can force you, because then you're left with something
substantial. But if you're going to be left with less than that,
I can't force you to split it. Okay fine, so that's called
יש בו דין חלוקה, yesh bo din chaluka, that big enough that
I can force a split of the yard. אין חולקין את החצר
עד שיהא בו ארבע אמות לזה וארבע אמות לזה. ein chokin es
hachatzer ad sheyehei bo arba amos leze ve'arba amos leze. היש בו
כדי לזה וכדי לזה חולקין. hayesh bo kedei leze vekedei leze chokin.
So once it is enough, I can force a split, and therefore
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו בכותל, mai lav bekosel, wouldn't that
mean that we would split it and create a wall? Which is
a very like begs the question type of a of an assumption.
But says lo, במסימתא. bemistama. What type of proof is that? I
can force you to split it and then we would make a
dividing line, you know, little pegs, it doesn't prove at all whether
we can force you to build a wall. Okay, תא שמע tashma
come and hear. החלונות, hachalonos,
if my neighbor has windows in his, you know, in his house
in his yard, and I'm trying to build a wall or structure
in my yard, בין מלמעלה בין מלמטה בין מכנגדן ארבע אמות. bein
mimalah bein mimatah bein miknegdan arba amos. If I want to build
something a wall, okay, you know, on my side of the property,
and this not forcing you I'm going to build a wall on
my side of the property and right on your side of the
property, right near that boundary line, you have a house with windows.
So my wall has to be either higher than the four amos
higher than your top window or four amos lower than your bottom
window and it has to be four amos away from your window.
So what's the reason? Okay, so it says מלמעלה, milmala, above it
has to be higher, if it's going to be higher than your
windows, it has to be four amos higher, כדי שלא יציץ ויראה,
kedei shelo yatzitz veyireh, so I should not be able to stand
on the top of my wall and look into your windows. I
probably can't even if it is higher, but it'll be harder, okay,
so it has to make it like not as easy, if I'm
standing on top of my wall, it can't be easy visual access
into your windows. So it has to be four amos higher. מלמטה
milmata and below, same idea, כדי שלא יעמוד ויראה, kedei shelo yaamod
veyireh, also you should not be able to stand on it and
look straight in. What? כדי שלא יעמוד ויראה, kedei shelo yaamod veyireh,
if you stand on top of the wall. I guess the assumption
is is that your window would be just above you. If the
window is here and the wall is four amos below and you're
standing, okay, four amos is about six feet and people then were
more like five feet tall, okay, so then you would be here,
so your sight would be, you know, whatever, if you're five and
a half feet and then your eyes are whatever at five feet,
right, so your eyesight is like an an so now of course
you could say I could look up, you know, I don't exactly
get it, you're right, but what? In the second case you're looking,
the second case is that it's but I presumably the person doesn't
have to stand right at the window and if you're looking up
through the window you can't see, that's true, that's a good point,
you could see like somebody right at the window, you couldn't get
a good access into the right, that's a good point too. Okay,
so let's say your house has windows and they're higher than, I
don't know, anyway, okay, מכנגדן, mikenegdan, כדי שלא יאפיל, kedei shelo yaapil,
and you have to give them a four amos away for a
very good reason so you should not block the guy's sunlight, okay,
right. So anyway fine, that's not our issue the last line. Anyway
what you see very clearly is you have to construct, you can't
construct a wall which even gives you the reasonable potential of looking
in, right? So you can't sort of create a scenario here where,
you know, so you're not even, you know,
it's not even blocking yourself from a natural looking in, it's not
even you can't even create a wall that gives you a reasonable
potential to look in, you have to help that person protect his
privacy in that regard. So it certainly seems like היזק ראיה שמו
היזק. hezek reiyah shemei hezek. Is it a case where they tear
down? Well that's a different discussion, we'll get to all that. So
הגמרא hagmarah says like this, okay, so כדי שלא kedei shelo so
הגמרא hagmarah says היזק דביתא שאני, hezeka dbeisa shani, no no no,
privacy in the home is a completely different matter. Until now there
was privacy in your yard. Certainly, you know, there's an issue of
being able to protect the right of privacy in your home and
somebody's ability to look in is seen as a real היזק hezek
and as a real damage and that person therefore has to take
steps to prevent that from happening or even to prevent the possibility
of that happening. Okay, so תא שמע. ta shema. So again we're
like conceding the point right and left, it's just a question of
the scope. Would it apply by a yard? Okay, תא שמע, ta
shema, come and hear, דאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל גג הסמוך לחצר
חבירו עושה לו מעקה גבוה ארבע אמות. deamar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel
gag hasamuch lachatzer chaveiro oseh lo maakeh gavoha arba amos.
So I have my rooftop which is flat, right, they had the
ability to use their rooftops, is right up against our boundary line.
So I can go to my rooftop, have a nice little picnic
on my roof and look straight down into your yard. Okay, any
a wall is not going to do any good, right, a wall
on the ground. I'm just going to look straight down into your
yard. So what I have to do now on my rooftop is
to build a wall on my rooftop, okay, a מעקה maakeh anyway,
but this has to be four amos. Exactly, it has to be
a height not just to prevent people from falling, but to prevent
me from looking. All right, so כדי שלא kedei shelo so הגמרא
hagmarah
says, כדי שלא kedei shelo no, so you see that's a case
of היזק ראיה hezek reiyah of a חצר. chatzer. So הגמרא hagmarah
says no, שאני התם דאמרי ליה בחצר לבעל גג, shani asam deamrei
leh bachatzer livaal gag, no, because there the owner of the yard
could say to the owner of the roof, לדידי קביעא לי תשמישתא
לדידך לא קביעא לך תשמישתא. lididi kevia li tashmishta lididach lo kevia
lach tashmishta. The yard is something I use on a regular basis.
The rooftop you use occasionally once a month you decide to have
like a little picnic on your roof. ולא ידענא בהי עידנא דסליקת
ואתית, velo yadana behei idna desalikat veasis,
and I don't know exactly when is the time you're going to
decide to go up onto your rooftop דאיצטנע מינך, deitzatna minach, that
I could take precautions protecting myself against you, which means what? Which
means yet to be צנוע, tzanua, to be מצניע matznia myself, to
if I know you're going to be on your rooftop I won't
do certain things, but I don't know whether you're going to be
on your rooftop or not. Okay, so if you look at רשי,
Rashi, right, רשי Rashi says דברי הצנע, divrei hatzneiah, and וחצר
החלוקה, vechatzer hachaluka, top רשי Rashi ג עמוד ב, gimmel amud beis,
וחצר החלוקה vechatzer hachaluka לתרוייהו קביעא תשמישתא לכל אחד, letravaihu kevia tashmishta
lechol echad,
everybody regularly uses their yard כל שעתא, kol shaata, ולא עבידי בני
אינשא דצנעא, velo avidi bnei inasha ditzina,
and folks won't do a private thing which basically means what? Because
it's interesting because you could frame it as it's היזק ראיה hezek
reiyah that you're preventing me from doing certain usage. Meaning it's not
היזק ראיה. hezek reiyah. The היזק hezek is the limiting of my
freedom of use of my yard because I know that you're looking
in. But apparently
היזק ראיה. hezek reiyah. So in the case of you have a
roof and I have a whatever, because you're rarely there, I'm going
to operate with a sense of freedom to use it. I'm not
going to not use it because once a month you're going to
go up there. And therefore that time that you do go up
once a month, you will be invading my types of private activities.
Okay, whereas in the other case, the we would if the with
the absence of a wall, we would start with the assumption that
I'm not going to do private activities. So there's nothing being invaded.
Of course, that might exactly be the גמרא's Gemara's question, right? It's
an interesting way of reframing the question. One is once you already
have a presumption of privacy and somebody is coming and invading it,
is that a היזק? Hezek? And that would be sort of like
the case, you know, of the house or תוספות Tosafot said the
case where the wall fell where we all already were used to
doing private activities. In this case of the rooftop and the yard.
So there's a presumption of privacy and an established norm of private
activities and it's being invaded. That's one type of a היזק. Hezek.
Is the maybe the question of the yard is is that a
starting default position where you have people looking in and therefore you
are not you're going to restrain yourselves from doing these activities, right?
So it's not that you have a private activity being invaded, you
have a non-perform the lack of freedom to do certain private activities,
is that also considered a היזק? Hezek? So maybe that's the way
of why the גמרא Gemara seems, you know, maybe it's maybe that
sort of what makes it sort of a something of a qualitatively
different question, right? Because you understand the difference? It's not like the
activity's being invaded, it's like the activity isn't being done in the
first place because of the setup. Okay, so we still don't know
the answer to that question. Of in a case of a yard,
can I force the other person to build a wall? Is that
a היזק ראייה Hezek Re'iyah case? Yes, there is היזק ראייה, Hezek
Re'iyah, but is that a is that a case
of
היזק ראייה? Hezek Re'iyah? Yes, Eli. There's nothing of this to disprove.
It's a question about you're right. Meaning since there is all of
this evidence that it seems like it's שמי היזק, shmei Hezek, why
are we pushing so hard to try to say oh maybe חצר
chatzer is different. So the bottom reason is because it's just פשט
pshat of the read of the first line of the משנה. Mishnah.
The פשט pshat of the read of the first line of the
משנה Mishnah is is that you only have to build a wall
when it's agreed upon, that you can't force somebody to build a
wall. But you're right, all the evidence mounting up is that היזק
ראייה שמי היזק. Hezek Re'iyah shmei Hezek. Why should we try to
work to make all these distinctions? Yes. No, just to understand with
the case of this wall, it's like על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו,
al hamazik leharchik et atzmo, right? Right, we said that that היזק
ראייה Hezek Re'iyah could be שמי היזק shmei Hezek and you could
still argue על הניזק. al hanizak. But what I'm getting to is,
like, you know, tech can change these days or you can just
say I just draw the shutter or the blinds. Right, so that's
going to be a question too, what like other ways of addressing
it. Yes. Is there any distinction between being trespassed by somebody else
seeing you and not even doing the activity because you're afraid of
doing it? Exactly. That's even worse in a way, right? I mean
because that's like a built-in fear. Right. You could say it's worse
but you could also say that, you know, you have to determine
what sort of the status quo is, right? You know, maybe the
norms are that if if nobody builds walls and nobody can force
people to build walls to divide their yards, then the norm is
that yards are used for certain types of activities and not other
activities, right? The norm is that people don't sunbathe in their yards
because people don't have walls between their yards, right? So you know,
so it's a question about like what is your you know, what's
your right or what's your presumption of your But yeah, that's exactly
I think a way to phrase what the question is. Yeah. It's
not only about something sunbathe but like hung drying food, you know,
fruit, like clothes. Your laundry. You're doing stuff. Right, anything that's
private that's activity that you don't want every other people seeing for
whatever reason. Right. So you're right. I mean, like hanging up your
laundry, right, I don't want people seeing my my undergarments hanging up
on the line or whatever the case might be. Right. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, okay, so now look
גמרא Gemara now it's going to be we're a little now the
next couple of section. There you go. The next section is going
to go very quick because it's the same thing going from the
reverse direction. Let's take a look. Okay, אמרי לה, amri la, לישנא
אחרינא אמרי לה, lishna achrina amri la, another way that this was
said is that the argument started on the opposite side, that we
assumed to read the משנה Mishnah that you were dividing and you
can force a wall. Okay, which makes everything היזק ראייה. Hezek Re'iyah.
לישנא אחרינא אמרי לה, lishna achrina amri la, סברו savru מאי מחיצה
mai mechitza פלגתא. pulgtza. No, מחיצה mechitza means that you wanted to
make a division, not that and people agreed to make a division,
not a wall. דכתיב ותהי מחצית העדה. dechtiv vatehi mechtzat ha'edah. וכיון
דרצו, vekivan de-ratzu,
as soon as they agreed, בונין את הכותל על כרחן, bonin et
hakotel al karchan, and you can force somebody to build the wall.
אלמא היזק ראייה שמי היזק, alma Hezek Re'iyah shmei Hezek, you see
that it is considered היזק, Hezek, which is certainly what all the
other evidence seems to point to. Says the גמרא, Gemara, no, that's
not necessarily a proof. אימא eima I can say מאי מחיצה mai
mechitza גודא, guda, it's a wall. דתניא מחיצת הכרם שנפרצה אמרו לו
גדור detanya mechitza hakerem shenifretza amru lo gedor נפרצה אמרו לו גדור
נתייאש הימנה ולא גדרה הרי זה קידש וחייב באחריותה. nifretza amru lo
gedor nityashem mimenu velo gadrah harey zeh kidesh vechayav be'achrayuta. Like we
see by the case of כלאים, Kilayim, that the word מחיצה mechitza
means a wall, so it could mean a wall. And therefore Time
and therefore that would be the way to read the משנה mishna
then would be, the טעמא דרצה taama d'rotza only because you agreed
to make a wall. הא לא רצה, Ha lo rotza, if you
didn't agree, לא מחייבינן ליה, lo mechayivinan leh, you could not force
the person, אלמא היזק לאו שמיה היזק. alma hezek lav shemeh hezek.
So it would not be. So again, the question is all rides
on that question of how to read the משנה: mishna: is it
because you agree to make a division or agree to make a
wall? Here we're starting with the assumption that the לישנא אחרינא lishana
acharina starts with the reading that it's because you agree to make
a division. Okay, so אי הכי, i hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara,
one minute.
If it means that it's a, if the word מחיצה mechitzah were
to mean wall, אי הכי בונין את הכותל, i hachi bonin et
hakotel, why would it say build the wall? בונין אותו מיבעי ליה?
bonin oto miba'ei leh? If the word מחיצה mechitzah meant wall, it
should have just said בונין אותו. bonin oto. No, אלא מאי, ella
mai, so what do you want to say, פלוגתא? plugta? It means
you that they wanted to make a division? מחיצה mechitzah means division?
אי הכי שרצו לעשות מחיצה, i hachi sheratzu la'asot mechitzah, shouldn't say
they wanted to make a division, שרצו לחצות מיבעי ליה? sheratzu lachatzot
miba'ei leh? Should have said they wanted to divide it. Why do
you make it a noun, make it a verb? No, כדי אמשכי,
kedei amshchi, that's not a question, because that's the way people talk.
תנא עביד פלוגתא, tana avid plugta, let's make a division. Okay, so
you can sometimes speak in a noun and you don't have to
use it as a verb. All right, so fine, it's the same
point, but just arguing to read the משנה mishna as division and
היזק ראיה שמיה היזק. hezek reiah shemeh hezek. So the גמרא Gemara
says, היזק ראיה שמיה היזק, hezek reiah shemeh hezek, if that's true,
מאי איריא שרצו? mai irya sheratzu? אפילו לא רצו נמי. afilu lo
ratzu nami. So now this is like a funny question, but it's
like why do you have to agree to divide? Why can't I
just go to you and say, you have to make a wall?
But there's an obvious answer: you have to agree to divide because
until that point we're partners in the yard and we don't have
separate yards. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן משנתינו כשאין בה דין חלוקה, amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishnateinu keshein bah din chalukah, and here clarifies even more based on
what we just said. If there was a big enough yard, you
don't have to agree to divide it. I can force you to
divide it. I can force you to divide the yard and according
to this I can force you to build a wall. Okay, if
the yard is big enough, if you each get four אמות. amot.
But if the yard is not big enough, I can't force you
to divide the yard and you have to agree to divide the
yard. And I can't force you to build a wall? No, we're
now having the reading that once I can, once we're dividing, I
can force a
wall. Even with a small? Even with a small yard, yeah, exactly.
Okay, כשאין בה דין חלוקה, keshein bah din chalukah, it's not big
enough to naturally warrant a division. Okay, and therefore I can't force
you to divide, but if you agree to divide, then I can
force you to build a wall. והוא שרצו, vehu sheratzu, so you
have to agree to divide. Once we're dividing according to this read
of the משנה, mishna, you can force the wall. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, מאי קמשמע לן, mai kamashma lan, what is this
teaching us? דכי לית בה דין חלוקה כי רצו פלגי? dechi leis
bah din chalukah ki ratzu palgi? It's just here to teach us
that if it's small and it's not naturally divided, you can divide
it once it's agreed upon? תנינא, tanina, we know that. אימתי, eimatai,
when is it true
that if it's אין בה דין חלוקה ein bah din chalukah you
cannot, you don't divide it? בזמן שאין שניהם רוצים, bizman she'ein shneihem
rotzim, if they don't agree. אבל בזמן ששניהם רוצים, aval bizman sheshneihem
rotzim, if they both agree, אפילו פחות מכאן חולקין, afilu pachot mikan
cholkin, even a small yard you can agree, you can divide. So
what's the point of the משנה? mishna? Of course if you agree
to divide it, you divide it. Of course, the point is the
wall, exactly! אי מהתם הוה אמינא, ei mehatam hava amina, אפילו פחות
מכאן במצרא דעלמא, afilu pachot mikan bemitzra d'alma, all that would have
taught me was that if you agree to divide, you divide and
make a boundary line. Okay, but the whole point of the משנה
mishna is the wall. קמשמע לן הכא כותל, kamashma lan hacha kotel,
here the whole point is the wall. And according to this read,
once you agree to divide it, and if it's big enough you
don't even have to agree to divide it, but even if it's
small, if you agree to divide it and you then divide it,
then you can force a wall because היזק ראיה שמיה היזק. hezek
reiah shemeh hezek. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, ולתני הא ולא
לתני הך, u'lisni ha velo lisni hach, so why not just teach
our משנה mishna that if you agree to divide, you divide and
make a wall? Why do we need a later משנה mishna that
says if it's small you can't force a division but you can
divide once it's agreed upon, if that idea is already implicit in
our משנה? mishna? סיפא אצטריכא ליה, seifa itztericha leh,
no, that later משנה mishna is to tell you other הלכות halachot
about when you can force a division and so on. Because the
end of that משנה mishna later says, ובכתבי הקדש אף על פי
ששניהם רוצים לא יחלוקו. u'v'kitvei hakodesh af al pi sheshneihem rotzim lo
yachloku. If we jointly own a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, okay, it
doesn't matter if we want to say, look, I'm going to take
בראשית Breishit through half of ויקרא Vayikra because you know there's a
פסוק pasuk יש חצי התורה בידין במילים, yesh chatzi hatorah yad b'milim,
so רצו רצו, ratzu ratzu,
so we'll cut it right there, you take half, I take the
other half, that you can't do. So there are some things that
even if you agree upon, you can't divide. So the point of
that משנה mishna was to tell you there are some things if
you agree upon you can divide,
a small yard, there are other things that you can't divide. But
our משנה mishna assumes that, the way we're reading it, that it's
so small you can't force a division, but once you agree to
a division, then you can force a wall. Yeah, but especially if
you only had our משנה mishna you wouldn't know that our משנה
mishna was talking about... I know, that's even the better answer. If
it were only our משנה mishna you wouldn't know that there are
these different types of sizes of fields. That's really what the גמרא
Gemara should have said. Okay, let's go on, let's now keep going.
Okay, and we're going to skip the parentheses. הדרן עלך. hadran alach.
Yeah, I know. Okay, go to two דף daf to about four
lines before the lines get wide after the two dots. Now, גמרא
ומוקי לה למתניתין. Gemara u'moki lah l'masnithin. So now we're going to
go with this read of the גמרא. Gemara. Now, the גמרא's Gemara
אוקימתא למשנתנו. ukimta lemishnatenu. So now we're going to go with this
read of the משנה, Mishnah, that the משנה Mishnah is a small
yard. If you agree to divide it, you divide it, and then
you force a wall. היזק שמיה היזק. Hezek shemei hezek. Now we're
going to go with that reading. And it's a bigger yard, then
you can even force the division and force the wall. Force the
division and therefore force the wall. במאי אוקימתא למתניתין? Be-mai ukimta le-matnitin?
What are you saying our משנה's Mishnah talking about? בשאין בה דין
חלוקה. Be-she-ein bah din chalukah.
It's small, it's so small that you can't force a division. Okay,
אי בשאין בה דין חלוקה, Ei be-she-ein bah din chalukah, now, it
wasn't, it was so small you couldn't force a division, but if
you agree then you have to divide it. So now in this
little line of the גמרא, Gemara, it raises a very important question.
The גמרא Gemara says, כי רצו מאי הוי? נהדרו בהו! Ki ratzu
mai havei? Nahadru behu! So what if I agreed to divide it?
Let me, you know, I can just back out. Now this is
the question about like verbal contracts. It's not even verbal contracts. We
could do a קנין, kinyan, okay? We could write it down, we
could write it down in a contract. But the גמרא Gemara is
basically saying this is a very important principle of קנין דברים. kinyan
devarim. קנין דברים Kinyan devarim doesn't mean we just used our words
to obligate ourselves. We could have done it with a handkerchief, we
could make, sign a contract, but it means, or maybe קנין דברים,
kinyan devarim, excuse me, is not the right word, the phrase. The
phrase is קנין kinyan is like אומר אתן. omer eten. I used
the wrong phrase. It's אומר אתן, omer eten, to promise to do
something. Okay, there is no, you can't really have like a contract
to compel performance. What you can have is, you can have something
that sort of, well let's take a look. Let's read a little
bit more. So the גמרא Gemara says so what if you agreed
to divide it? You can't do something to obligate yourself to perform
something. Okay? אי בשאין בה דין חלוקה כי רצו מאי הוי? נהדרו
בהו! Ei be-she-ein bah din chalukah ki ratzu mai havei? Nahadru behu!
Let's just retract, let's just back out of it. אמר רב אסי
אמר רבי יוחנן שקנו מידן. Amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan she-kanu
mi-yadan. You did a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, you know, you did
the handkerchief thing that's supposed to bind you. And now the גמרא
Gemara says who cares? וכי קנו מידן מאי הוי? קנין דברים בעלמא
הוא! Ve-chi kanu mi-yadan mai havei? Kinyan devarim be-alma hu! I was,
that was the right phrase. Okay. It's קנין דברים kinyan devarim which
means, like I said, this is קנין דברים kinyan devarim is a
little bit, it's a little like confusing because that sounds like the
act of קנין kinyan wasn't strong enough. But it means it's just
a קנין kinyan to do what you promised. Which is sometimes why
it's framed as this other thing I called, which is like an
אומר אתן. omer eten. Okay, you cannot normally, if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, very important רש"י, Rashi, let's read רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
says,
קנין דברים בעלמא, kinyan devarim be-alma, it's right, it's near the top,
it's like eight lines from the lines get narrow from towards the
top. רש"י Rashi or whatever, like four lines above the line above
רבנו גרשום. Rabbeinu Gershom. ואין חליפין קונין, Ve-ein chalipin konin, this קנין
kinyan only works, like this handkerchief, אלא דבר הנקנה, ella davar ha-nikneh,
like you're actually transferring an object, או מכר או מתנה, o mecher
o matanah, either sale or a gift, או שעבוד קרקעות, o shibud
karkaot, or you're putting a lien on your land. Like you can
create a debt, I can do a קנין kinyan and owe you
a hundred dollars through that act of קנין kinyan even though I
didn't really borrow any money because I created a reality of a
lien and of a debt. שהקנין חל עליו או מטלטלין. She-ha-kinyan chal
alav o mitaltelin. Either that takes effect on the land or on
my property. This has to do with הלכה halacha being a very
sort of concrete reality and not these abstract, the same way you've
heard before people talk about that הלכה halacha doesn't have a developed
idea of corporation, right? It's very concrete. So therefore I can, now,
for, I'll give you an interesting contrast. תוספות Tosafot says this question
of how the קנין kinyan worked was not asked before in the
discussion about building the wall. Right? Before we assumed you couldn't force
a wall, but if you agree to make a wall, you have
to make it. Well, what obligates me to make a wall? תוספות
Tosafot says no, that's different. Because if I'm agreeing to make a
wall, what I'm basically saying is I'm going to contribute to the
expenses or whatever. So I'm creating a reality as it were about
like a lien on my property. I've obligated myself financially. The key
word is financially. Okay, so if I agree to contribute to the
building of a wall, it doesn't mean I'm agreeing to do something
physically, I'm going to go and actually שלעפ schlep the stones, right?
I'm agreeing to a financial obligation. So you could create a financial
debt, a financial obligation. But to agree to divide a yard, it's
not creating a financial reality. You can divide the yard, but to
agree to divide the yard in the future, you're not transferring property,
you're not creating a financial obligation. So what are you doing? Right?
Now ironically, you might be able to create a sense of a
penalty if I don't divide the yard. That would actually create a
reality of a financial obligation. You might get into אסמכתא asmachta issues.
But you're creating a reality of a debt and of a penalty.
But to actually just סתם stam obligate me to do something in
the future is not a type of a mechanism that the הלכה
halacha has. Now the difference is, and I mentioned this at the
end of בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, an idea of שכירות. sechirut. Like
I can basically hire myself out to do a labor. Okay, because
the תורה Torah recognizes this category called שכירות. sechirut. תוספות Tosafot says
it's like שומרים. shomrim. You're a שומר, shomer, you do a קנין,
kinyan, you obligate yourself in different levels, תוספות Tosafot says ah, but
what that does is that creates a financial obligation on you in
case the object gets destroyed. So there there's a reality of a
financial obligation because what you're really obligating yourself is in some conceptual
way, not the act of watching, but the liability if I don't
do the act of watching. incorrectly. So liability you can assume, okay.
Transfer of property you can assume. Debt you can create. But just
סתם stam I promise to do something, you know, I remember when
I was growing up once there was this this whole discussion about
a guy who like
asked this girl out to the prom and then he and then
he basically backed out and she wanted to sue him for breach
of oral contract, okay. So like just a promise to do something
even with a קנין, kinyan, okay, or you know that does not
create a legal construct. David, would you want to say something about
that? Well, the question that I have is if agreeing to divide
means that you've essentially agreed to build the wall, then you have
agreed to a monetary commitment, you have agreed to make a monetary...
No, because I didn't agree to build the wall. After we've divided,
then you can impose on me as it were almost, you know,
one is like laws of contracts, right? The other, I'm not agreeing
to build a wall. I could say, you know, but after it's
it's divided, you can impose on me the obligation to build a
wall because of the potential היזק hezek I'm creating for you. Right,
but I mean using that same kind of language of of that
I can
obligate myself to to pay money. Right, I can create liability and
financial obligation and so on. So if when I say that I
am willing to divide, I have effectively said right, but if you
want to build a wall as a result, I will contribute, you
can... the question is... But but I think we're not necessarily assuming
that. Right, we're not necessarily reading that as a contractual obligation, we're
reading that as something that emerges after the fact. But right, yeah.
But can I then give you a square inch of קרקע karka
in exchange you agree to divide the... I mean, like... No, it's
not about the problem of the מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, it's about
what the קנין kinyan is obligating. Let's keep with that. Yeah, let's
read the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי קנו
מידו מאי הוי? Vechi kanu miyado mai havay? So very important גמרא
Gemara implicit in this like one line about how what the limit
of sort of of legal obligations are. וכי קנו מידו מאי הוי
קנין דברים בעלמא הוא. Vechi kanu miyado mai havay kinyan devarim be'alma
hu. בשקנו מידם ברוחות. Beshekannu miyadam beruchot. So רש"י Rashi says, if
basically the רש"י Rashi translates this, I'm not agreeing to divide in
the future. We actually did divide. So basically I say Michael, I
know it's a small yard, but would you agree to divide it?
Yes. Good. Okay. You take every this the south side, I take
the north side. Whoa, we do a קנין kinyan and that קנין
kinyan actually effects the division. That we can do. We can actually
divide it. We can't commit to divide it in the future in
a binding way. The קנין kinyan is to verify the past. What?
So this קנין kinyan is to verify... Not to verify... to create
a new reality. It gives you half ownership of full ownership of
your half and me full ownership of my half. It creates an
actual monetary reality. Okay, בשקנו מידם ברוחות. Beshekannu miyadam beruchot. רש"י אמר
כגון שהלך זה בתוך שלו והחזיק וזה בתוך שלו והחזיק. Rashi amar
kigon shehalach zeh betoch shelo vehachzik vezeh betoch shelo vehachzik. It's really
a variation of it. You didn't do it through a קנין סודר
kinyan sudar through a handkerchief. We said Michael you take the north
half, I take the south half, you go to your side of
the yard and you you know do some חזקה, chazakah, you know,
some act of of like fixing a fence. I go to my
side... Like an actual tree? Like we had... No, no, no. I
go on my side and we actually do it through a קנין
חזקה. kinyan chazakah. Fine. But one way or the other the גמרא
Gemara says you cannot commit in a binding way to divide, you
can divide but you can't commit to divide. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara goes on. מקום שנהגו לבנות. Makom shenahagu livnot. Now we get
to an easier, now we're sort of moving from that whole conceptual
aspect, right, about היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah and that really important question
about קנין דברים kinyan devarim and now we're getting to a more
just a more הלכה halachah concrete part about which is the building
materials. All right, anyway so the גמרא Gemara says, okay people missed
that part. All right, the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, מקום
שנהגו לבנות. Makom shenahagu livnot. The גמרא Gemara says גוויל, gevil, now
we're just going to explain the different building materials mentioned in the
משנה Mishnah based on what the מנהג minhag is. גוויל, Gevil, so
גוויל gevil is אבני דלא משפיא, avnei dela mashpaya, are stones that
have not been smoothed. גזית, Gazit, אבני דמשפיא, avnei demashpaya, stones that
have been smoothed, דכתיב כל אלה אבנים יקרות כמדות גזית, dechtiv kol
eileh avanim yekarot kemiddot gazit, all of these are like dear stones
or weighty stones like the like hewn stones, okay, גזית gazit is
a hewn stone. What? Expensive. Well, yeah, I don't I know יקר,
yakar, I would I didn't know you could translate it either way,
right? It can either be dear when I said dear I meant
expensive, okay, but it could be expensive or it could be weighty.
I assume it means expensive. Anyway fine. כפיסין Kefisin are אריחי. arichei.
Those are like half bricks. לבנים Leveinim are לבני, livnei, those are
full bricks. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, Amar lei
Rav Acha bereih deRava leRav Ashi, ממאי דגוויל אבני דלא משפיא נינהו?
mimai degevil avnei dela mashpaya ninhu? How do you know גוויל gevil
are non-smoothed stones? והא טפח יתירא למושב דקרנא? Veha tefach yeseira lemoshav
dekarna? And
the reason גוויל gevil is one טפח tefach wider, six טפחים tefachim
as opposed to the גזית gazit which is five טפחים. tefachim. The
reason it's one טפח tefach wider is because of the like the
corners, you know, the edges, if it's rough it obviously sticks out
so it's taking more space, okay? ודילמא? Udilma? Maybe the reason that
the גוויל gevil is wider is פלגא דגזית הוא? palga degazit hu?
Maybe it's nice smooth stone, but it's two halves, two halves that
are that are put together with some like plaster in the middle
and that extra plaster is what gives it the extra טפח tefach
*tefach*. והאי טפח tefach יתירה לביני אורבי הוא *ve'hai tefach yeteira leveinei
urbai hu*, and that extra טפח tefach *tefach* of the גוויל *gvil*
is for the plaster between the stones or the cement. Now why
should I say that? Parallel to the last two cases in the
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. כדאמרינן כפיסין ארכי *kide'amrinan kfisin archi*, like we say
כפיסין *kfisin* are half bricks which are kept together with cement and
that's why the total width is larger. לבנים ולבנים ארבע *leveinim u'leveinim
arba*. לבנים *leveinim* are שלוש *shalosh*, לבנים *leveinim* are לבני *livnei*. והאי
טפח tefach יתירה *ve'hai tefach yeteira*, the reason these half bricks are
a טפח tefach, *tefach* wider, four rather than three of the whole
bricks, is because of והאי טפח tefach יתירה לביני אורבי *ve'hai tefach
yeteira leveinei urbai*, is for the cement between the bricks. So why
don't we say the same here too? It's that it's smooth stones,
but it's got two halves and cement between them. אמר ליה Amlei
ולטעמך *amar lei u'leta'ameich*, and according to your reasoning, כפיסין ארכי מנלן
*kfisin archi minalan*? How do you know כפיסין *kfisin* are half bricks?
How do you know what anything in the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* means?
אלא גמרא Gemara גמירי gemiri, לה *ela gemara gemiri lah*. We have
a tradition that that's what the word כפיסין *kfisin* means: half bricks
kept together with cement. So גוויל נמי אבני דלא משפיא *gvil nami
avnei d'la mashpaya*? So how do we know גוויל *gvil* means unsmoothed
stones? Also גמרא Gemara גמירי לה *gemara gemiri lah*, it's a tradition.
Well how do you argue? Because this means this and this means
this. It's like these are all building materials, they mean what they
mean. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri
*ika de'amri*, some say, אמר ליה Amlei רב אחא בריה דרב אויא
לרב אשי *amar lei Rav Acha breih de'Rav Avya le'Rav Ashi*, the
same question except in the reverse. מנא ידעינן כפיסין ארכי *mena yadainan
kfisin archi*? How do you know כפיסין *kfisin* are half bricks and
they're wider because they're half bricks kept together with cement? והאי טפח
tefach יתירה לביני אורבי *ve'hai tefach yeteira leveinei urbai* and the extra
טפח tefach *tefach* is for the cement between the bricks. דילמא מאי
כפיסין *dilma mai kfisin*, maybe what are כפיסין *kfisin*? אבני דלא משפיא
*avnei d'la mashpaya*.
Maybe כפיסין *kfisin* are basically like unsmoothed bricks. והאי טפח tefach יתירה
למורשא דקרנתא *ve'hai tefach yeteira lemorsha dekarnata*, the extra טפח tefach *tefach*
is because of the, you know, the protrusions. כדאמרינן *kide'amrinan* like we
say by the stones, גוויל אבני דלא משפיא *gvil avnei d'la mashpaya*,
that גוויל *gvil* is unsmoothed stones, גזית gazit, אבני דמשפיא *gazit avnei
demashpaya*, and גזית gazit. *gazit* is smooth stones, והאי טפח tefach יתירה
למורשא דקרנתא *ve'hai tefach yeteira lemorsha dekarnata*, the extra טפח tefach *tefach*
is for the protrusions. So maybe the same way that's what it
means by the stones, that's what it should mean by the bricks.
אמר ליה ולטעמך *amar lei u'leta'ameich*, according to you, גוויל אבני דלא
משפיא מנלן *gvil avnei d'la mashpaya minalan*? How do you know גוויל
*gvil* means unsmoothed stones? How do you know anything means anything here?
אלא גמרא Gemara גמירי לה *ela gemara gemiri lah*, that's our tradition.
הכא נמי *hacha nami*, here too by the bricks, גמרא Gemara גמירי
לה *gemara gemiri lah*, tradition is that it's not that it's unsmooth,
it's that it's two halves that are kept together by cement. Okay,
wonderful. אמר אביי amar Abaye, *amar Abaye*, moving on, שמע מינה shma
mina, *shma mina*, we can infer from this משנה mishna *Mishnah*, כל
ביני אורבי טפח tefach *kol beinei urbai tefach*, that the sort of
the cement that you use to combine two half stones is going
to be a טפח tefach *tefach*. Okay, and רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says
why do I care? What do you mean? Okay. רש״י Rashi *Rashi*
says ונפקא מינה *u'nafka mina* says רש״י *Rashi*, לקבל עליו לבנות כותל
לחבירו *lekabel alav livnot kotel lechavero*.
I contract to build a wall, you can come and say hey
you built it below code because you only have a half טפח
tefach *tefach* of cement between the bricks, not a full טפח tefach
*tefach*. So from our משנה mishna *Mishnah* we see that the standard
is a full טפח tefach *tefach* of cement between the half bricks
and therefore that is implicitly therefore a standard that you can, you
know, demand from others that are contracting to do this. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: הני מילי בטינא *hani mili
betina*, now that's if you use טינא *tina*, I think plaster, אבל
בריכסא *aval berichsa*, ריכסא *richsa* רש״י *Rashi* says is more like small
pebbles with some cement, so it's not the same type of, it's
not as strong. Mortar and cement are two different things. One is
smooth and one's got
like
pebbles. Okay so this one is mortar. Mortar is the one with
the pebbles? No. Cement is the one with the pebbles? I think
in English, I think mortar is smooth between bricks and cement has
got rocks. Fine, so we'll go with that. The טינא *tina* thing,
it's not בטון *beton*?
The
ב *bet* is part? Is it? Because ריכסא *richsa* the ב *bet*
is not... no, טינא *tina*, maybe in Hebrew but טינא *tina* in
Aramaic is... טינא *tina* in Aramaic is plaster. The ב *bet* here
means with. What? טינא *tina* is הלא בלבו טינא *halo belibo tina*.
Don't they work
with בחמר ובלבנים *be'chomer u'vileveinim*? Anyway moving on. Okay, we can look
up the grammar later. But טינא *tina* in Aramaic, the ב *bet*
here means with. It's not the... הני מילי בטינא *hani mili betina*.
That's if you use mortar without the pebbles and therefore you need
less of it. אבל בריכסא *aval berichsa*, if you use the stuff
with the pebbles then בעי טפי *bei tfei*, you need more than
just a טפח tefach *tefach*. איכא דאמרי *ika de'amri*, some say the
opposite. הני מילי בריכסא *hani mili berichsa*, that's if you're using the
stuff with the pebbles. אבל בטינא *aval betina*, if you're using the
טינא *tina*, לא בעי כולי האי *la bei kuli hai*, you don't
need a full טפח tefach *tefach*. Fine, moving on. ולמימרא דבגזית כל
ארבע אמות גובה kol arba amos govah, אי הוי פותיא חמישה קאי
kai, לא לא קאי *u'lemeimra de've'gazit kol arba amot gova ei havei
putya chamisha kai lo lo kai*. So it's a pity that Michael
left because this answers a question that Michael was bothered with, which
is this: If the reason you are compelling in the משנה *Mishnah*
is because of היזק ראיה *hezek re'iya* and therefore it's about height,
why does the משנה *Mishnah* not, you know, emphasize width? A later
משנה *Mishnah* speaks about ארבע אמות amos *arba amot*, but why don't
I just care about the height? Why do I also care about
the width? So the obvious point is that well no, if you're
going to get it a certain height and you want it with
a certain building material, then you need a certain width to support
that height based on the building material. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says okay so wait a minute. So it sounds... Like since
the standard height is four אמות, amos to get something that's a
good standard, good stability and size of four אמות amos high if
I'm using these גזית, gazit, these hewn stones, it only needs to
be five טפחים tefachim wide because that's what the משנה said. Five
טפחים tefachim of stones to get a four טפח tefach high of
no, four אמות amos high of גזית. Okay, so that's the implication.
So let's read that again. למימרא דבגזית, lema de-ve-gazit, if you're dealing
with this גזית, כל ארבע אמות amos, גובה, since the point is
to get the wall four אמות amos? high, יהבי פותיא חמשה, yehu
pischa chamisha, if its width is five טפחים, tefachim, קאי, it'll stand.
ואי לא לא קאי, ve-ilo lo kai, and if not, not. So
the גמרא Gemara says how can you say that? והא אמת טרכסין
ve-ha ammat traxin דהוי גבוה שלשים אמה, de-havei govah tlatin amhassa, we
have somebody here who did a whole paper on this. Okay, so
we've got a the there's the wall that separated the קדש Kodesh
from the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
was thirty אמות amos high in שלמה's Shlomo בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
and it was only an אמה amah wide. Okay, because it was
needed
to because that was sort of the line between the קדש Kodesh
and the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So if you get five טפחים,
tefachim, an אמה amah is six טפחים, tefachim, if you need five
טפחים tefachim to support four אמות, amos how could it be that
when you add one טפח tefach of width of six טפחים tefachim
you can now support thirty אמות? amos. והא אמת טרכסין ve-ha ammat
traxin דהוי גבוה שלשים אמה de-havei govah tlatin amhassa was thirty אמות
amos high, ולא הוי פותיא אלא שית פושכין, velo avei pascha ela
shis pushchin, it was only six טפחים tefachim wide. וקם, ve-kam, how
could that work? גמרא Gemara says no. כיון דאיכא טפח יתירה קאי,
keyvan de-ika tefach yeseira kai, yes, one extra טפח tefach does wonders.
Once you get it from five to six, now you can go
up from four אמות amos. to thirty אמות. amos, Okay, the גמרא's
Gemara going to have a better answer in a minute. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ובמקדש שני מאי טעמא לא עבדו
אמת טרכסין? u-ve-mikdash sheni mai ta'ama lo avdu ammat traxin? And in
the second בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, where the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
was much taller, so if an אמה amah can support thirty אמות
amos high, maybe let's make it even taller. Why didn't why didn't
you do a wall in the second בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, they
had curtains, but they didn't have a wall. Why not have a
wall? So the גמרא Gemara says no. כי קאי בשלשים קאי. ki
kai bi-tlatin kai. No, no, one אמה amah can only get you
up to thirty אמות. amos טפי לא קאי, tfei lo kai, higher
it couldn't. And because there was only one אמה amah width that
was allowed, because there was only one אמה amah that they knew,
like they didn't know on that side was the קדש Kodesh and
the other side was the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, there was this
one אמה amah where it wasn't exactly clear which part it was
a part of. You couldn't go more than an אמה amah wide.
Okay, you couldn't encroach into the zone of the other two spaces.
So and the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash was taller. So because you
couldn't go more than an אמה amah wide and the height was
taller, so one אמה amah would support thirty אמות, it wouldn't support
more. טפי לא קאי. tfei lo kai. גמרא Gemara says, ומנלן דהוי
גבוה טפי? u-minalan de-havei govah tfei? How do you know the second
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash was taller?
דכתיב גדול יהיה כבוד הבית האחרון מן הראשון. de-chtiv gadol yiheyeh kevod
ha-bayit ha-acharon min ha-rishon. The second בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash will be
greater than the first eventually, not initially. So גמרא Gemara says, רב
ושמואל ואמרי לה רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר, Rav u-Shmuel ve-amrei lah Rabbi
Yochanan ve-Rabbi Elazar, there's a debate. חד אמר בבנין וחד אמר בשנים.
chad amar be-vinyan ve-chad amar be-shanim. One says it'll be greater in
the actual construction, the actual building itself will be greater, which it
was in Herodian times, and the other said it will last for
more years. Okay, ואיתא להא ואיתא להא, ve-isa la-hai ve-isa la-hai, they're
both true. And by Herodian times they'd gotten so high that you
could no longer make a wall that wide you know, a wall
that high with only an אמה amah width at the base. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ונעביד שלשים אמין בבנין ואידך נעביד פרוכת? ve-ne'avid
tlatin ammin be-vinyan ve-idach ne'avid paroches? Okay, why not make thirty אמות
wall and the top of it, you know, if you want it
to reach the ceiling, you know, use curtains, but at least the
bottom make a wall. גמרא Gemara says no. כי קאי שלשים אמה
נמי אגב תקרה מזיוה הוי קאי בלא תקרה מזיוה לא הוי קאי,
ki kai tlatin amhassa nami agav tikrah maziva havei kai velo tikrah
maziva lo havei kai, which is a better answer than just the
extra טפח tefach did wonders, which is: if you have a supporting
ceiling to hold down the top of the wall, then you can
make it much taller. Free-standing wall can only be so high. A
wall that's going up to the ceiling and the ceiling is keeping
it down, whatever, and holds it and seals it, that can be
much taller. So if you're going to have curtains, you won't have
this support of the ceiling at the top of the wall. Okay?
So that's why you could not do the top ceilings. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ולעביד מאי דאפשר בבנין ולעביד אידך פרוכת? velo aveid
mai de-efshar be-vinyan velo aveid idach paroches? Fine, you couldn't do a
whole thirty אמות high because without the support of the ceiling. But
still, why not make, you know, as high as you can a
wall and the rest make with the curtain? At least the base
would be a wall like it was in the first בית המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash. So גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי, no, גמירי, we have
a tradition, אי כולה בבנין אי כולה בפרוכת. i-kula be-vinyan i-kula be-paroches.
You either have to do the whole thing with a wall or
the whole thing with a curtain. You can't have half and half.
אי כולה בבנין, i-kula be-vinyan, how do we know? Because we have
two models. אי כולה בבנין ממקדש, i-kula be-vinyan mi-mikdash, the first בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash it was all a wall. So if you want
to do all wall, do all wall. אי כולה בפרוכת i-kula be-paroches
and the curtain, ממשכן, mi-mishkan,
the משכן mishkan had a curtain, didn't have a wall. So one
or the other. You can't do half and half. And since it
was too high to do a wall, they had to do the
whole thing with a curtain. Okay. Do contemporary פוסקים poskim quote this
סוגיא sugya for מחיצה mechitza in the בתי כנסיות batei kenesset as
to why it's a separate room? Not that I know of. That's
that far they don't go. Okay. Yeah, there you go. That's true.
It's a good point, right? You know, let's true, like the same
with a little curtain at the bottom. All right, fine, got it.
Moving on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Shhh, okay.
איבעיא להו. iba'y-lehu. הן וסידן או דלמא הן בלא סידן. hein ve-sidan
o dilma hein belo sidan.
When we said... that this thing has to be six טפחים, tefachim,
five טפחים, tefachim, six טפחים, tefachim, three טפחים, tefachim, does it include
the plaster before we talk about the plaster between half-bricks? But how
about the plaster at the edges, right, at the extremities? Is the
entire width of the three טפחים tefachim or whatever of just the
brick or the brick plus the plaster at the extremities? Okay, הן
וסידן או דלמא הן בלא סידן. hen vesidan o dilma hen belo
sidan. Everyone's talking about it, מסתברא הן וסידן, Mistava hen besidan, it
presumably means together with the plaster. דאי סלקא דעתך הן בלא סידן,
di salka daitach hen belo sidan, if you think it means without
the plaster, ליתני לשיעורי lisnai leshiyurei tell me how much the whole
width is, tell me how much plaster you're obligated to do. Okay,
so since it doesn't, presumably it's telling you the total. אלא שמע
מינה הן וסידן, ela shema mina hen besidan,
so presumably it means with the plaster. So the גמרא Gemara pushes
back on this. לא ולעולם אימא לך הן בלא סידן lo, ve'elma
eimalach hen belo sidan even without the plaster. So why not tell
me how much plaster you need? וכיון דלא הוי טפח לא תני,
vekivan delo havei tefach lo tanei, since the extra amount of the
plaster wasn't a טפח, it didn't give you, it doesn't bother with
half amounts. Right, talks about a little thin layer of plaster that
goes over the front of the wall? No, maybe plaster's the wrong
word, I mean I think I mean cement. Are you talking about
the cement? The cement? Yeah, the cement. Yeah. Are you talking about
the cement that's sticking out in between the bricks? A sloppy masonry.
Yeah. What?
A sloppy masonry. Yeah. Oh I think he's talking about the plaster
that makes the whole stucco. Right, stucco, so then that's like, how
thin is that? Like a millimeter?
No, no, no, no, a טפח is a lot. Yeah, no, you're
right, you're right. רש"י Rashi says טיח הסיד, tiach hasid, so it
does sound like it is like the plaster, not the cement. But
it's thicker than what we do, but it's thin. Right, you're right,
you're right, it's not the cement to keep the bricks, it's the
plaster. It's the plaster, right, it's a stucco, right. Okay, thank you.
Oh, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא לך הן בלא סידן
וכיון דלא הוי טפח לא תני. ela eimalach hen belo sidan vekivan
delo havei tefach lo tanei. It's not going to tell you plus
point two טפח of plaster, okay? It's like your taxes, you round
off to the dollar.
But the גמרא Gemara says no, והקתני בלבנים, vehakatani bilveinim, but wait
a minute, we talk about, we talk about portions of a טפח
when we talk about the bricks, the half bricks, that or whatever,
then, actually the whole bricks, זה נותן טפח ומחצה וזה נותן טפח
ומחצה, zeh notein tefach umachetza vezeh notein tefach umachetza, you have to
give a half, one and a half טפחים tefachim of your yard
and the other guy one and a half טפחים tefachim of his
yard. He says no, התם חזי לאצטרופי, hasam chazei leitztarovei, that's because
the total is three טפחים. tefachim. Okay, here the total is going
to be three point three טפחים, tefachim, you know, because one and
a half, point one five טפח of plaster on each side, that's
why not going to say. All right, תא שמע, ta shema, so
maybe it is, the plaster is in addition to this and we're
just not going to bother mentioning it. תא שמע, ta shema, let's
try to prove it. הקורה שאמרו רחבה כדי לקבל אריח, hakora she'amru
rechava kedei lekabel ariach, so when you have for a courtyard, you
have to do a beam at the top in order you don't
have a fourth wall of the courtyard. So the way you make
a virtual fourth yard to allow you to carry is either you
make a לחי lechi a standing vertical sort of post or you
put some beam on the top. If you're going to put a
beam on the top to be a representative wall, it has to
be a טפח wide. Why does it have to be a טפח
wide? Because it has to be able to conceptually be like a
frame for building bricks on it. Why is it building bricks? Because
we learn here that a width of a brick is a טפח
and a half, right? These half bricks are a טפח and a
half. So if you now, so you'd have to be a טפח
and a half, but no, presumably if it's a טפח and a
half, you could put a brick stably on it with a quarter
טפח going out over each side. Okay, so the way we say
that a קורה kora has to be a טפח is it's wide
enough to put on it a טפח and a half brick, okay?
Which basically means it has to be a טפח wide. Wait, listen.
Isn't that three טפחים? tefachim? No, the, no remember the לבינה laveina
is three טפחים, tefachim, right? And the אריח, ariach, remember because the
משנה had these two half bricks, right, which is one and a
half and one and a half with this טפח of plaster in
the middle. Oh, so it's a half brick. It's a half brick,
yeah a half brick, right, right, right, a half brick,
right, right. Okay,
fine, okay. So it says הקורה שאמרו רחבה כדי לקבל אריח, hakora
she'amru rechava kedei lekabel ariach, right, not a לבינה, laveina, an אריח
ariach which is the half brick. האריח חצי לבינה של ג' טפחים.
ha'ariach chatzi laveina shel gimel tefachim. So, so here we're talking about
an אריח ariach that is just a טפח and a half and
it's not a total of three טפחים tefachim and we're still dealing
with something that is a non-full טפח size. So even if it's
not a full unit, we're going to mention its width. No, so
the says no, so I'm sorry, so yeah, no, no, that wasn't
the point, excuse me, that wasn't the point. The point was that
now that we see that an אריח ariach is a טפח and
a half, okay, and a לבינה laveina is three טפחים, tefachim, so
that answers our question. Excuse me, we're not talking about whether we
mention half units. It tells us that a לבינה laveina is three
טפחים tefachim and here we're not dealing with plaster, we're just dealing
with the brick itself, right? Because we're saying can the, is the
קורה kora support the brick, not support the brick? So it's telling
you a half brick is one and a half, a full brick
is three without the plaster. So that answers our question, it's without
the plaster. So the גמרא says like this. The גמרא says like
this. The גמרא
says התם ברברבתא. Hasam b'ravrevata. No, maybe that's big bricks are three
without the plaster. Maybe our משנה slightly smaller bricks that are three
with the plaster. דיקא נמי דקתני Dika nami d'katani and maybe you
can infer that from the language because it says של שלשה טפחים,
shel shlosha tfachim, a brick of three טפחים, tfachim, which means there
are some bricks that are not three טפחים. tfachim. So it doesn't
prove whether you know whether the standard is three טפחים, tfachim, that
brick it's talking about is three טפחים. tfachim. Okay, מכלל
דאיכא זוטא, mikh'lal d'ika zuta, presumably there are smaller ones as well.
שמע מינה, you can infer that. It's not everything is three טפחים.
tfachim. So we don't know if the width of the wall in
our משנה includes this small amount of plaster or not. Okay, yes,
I don't know it sounds like it concludes that way, it's pretty
open. Okay, now we've moved to a fascinating part of this because
the גמרא seems to completely switch tax and get into some really
interesting הלכה halakha about when can you tear down and rebuild a
שול, shul, okay, and it's a way of getting into just so
you know where we're going to circle back to the discussion of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, because we were discussing the height of
the wall of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and how the second
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was bigger and we're going to get into
a whole discussion of Herod's building of the second בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and how that was such a magnificent structure and it was
bigger than the first one and so on and the way we
get to that is by opening it with a halakhic discussion. Okay,
so let's take a look. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, said
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, לא לסתור איניש בי כנישתא עד דבני בי
כנישתא אחריתי. lo listor inish bei knishta ad d'bani bei knishta achrita.
Don't destroy a בי כנישתא bei knishta even if you're planning on
building another בי כנישתא, bei knishta, you know, you're doing it to
improve it, you have to have the second one built before you
destroy the first one. Of course very often you want to build
the second one on the land of the first one. Okay, but
why does he say you're not allowed to do this and we'll
see exceptions coming up in a minute. איכא דאמרי משום פשיעותא, mishum
pshiyuta, because of negligence. You just will dawdle and won't get around
to building it in a timely fashion and people won't have a
good place to
דאוון. daven. Actually no, I'm sorry, the דאוון daven comes up in
a minute. You just will be negligent and you won't actually do
it. ואיכא דאמרי V'ika d'amri and some say משום צלויי mishum tzloyi
because in the interim, not that you won't get around to doing
it, but in the interim you need a place to pray. The
גמרא says מאי בינייהו, mai beinayhu, what's the difference? איכא בינייהו דאיכא
Ika beinayhu d'ika and some have the גירסא girsa בי כנישתא אחריתי
bei knishta achrita and some have the גירסא girsa דוכתא לצלויי. duchta
l'tzloyi. You have some other place to pray. So you have some
other place to pray, it's not like I'm making people not have
a place to go to שול, shul, okay, but do I still,
let me do it or are we afraid that it's going to
take, if you know, if that that I can wind up, you
know, being negligent and taking years getting around and therefore before you
let me tear down one, it's better really be translating into the
building of another one. So the גמרא says like this. מרימר ומר
זוטרא, Mareimar u-Mar Zutra, now מרימר ומר זוטרא Mareimar u-Mar Zutra סתרי
ובנו בקייטא ובסיתווא, satri u-vani b'kayita u-v'sitva, they tore down the summer
בי כנישתא bei knishta in the winter
and the in the in the literally in the fall ובסיתווא בקייטא
u-v'sitva b'kayita and they tore down the fall or the winter one
in the summer. Now רש״י says the reason they're different is רש״י
says the winter one was like low ceilings and thick walls and
not a lot of windows so it retained heat and the summer
one was high ceilings, lot of windows, lot of air and it
was good for you know for getting it more airy. Anyway, so
here they did this. Now the question is so why did they
do this? This seems to פסקן pasken the side that the only
concern is the issue of a place to pray. So since it
was the summer and they were tearing down the winter one, right,
that's the time to rebuild the winter one is during the summer,
we have a place to pray, it's not a problem. So it
sounds like the whole issue is a place to pray, but if
the concern of negligence, so maybe you're going to still be negligent,
you won't get around to it. So תוספות Tosafot tries to explain
how this can work even within the approach of negligence, but certainly
on the face of this, this works best within the approach that
you just need to ensure that there's a place to pray. They
had two שולס, shuls, one they used in one season and one
they used in the other season? Correct. In the same location? Yeah,
I mean in the same town presumably, yeah. It's not because of
the location, it wasn't that they had, that's what I said, it
was because of how the שול shul was constructed.
Yeah, well it makes sense to me. Why doesn't it make sense
to you? Because one is light and airy and good circulation and
the other retains heat. You build one that's good for all year
round. All right, that's you that have insulation. Close the windows in
the winter. Fine. Anyway. Or build two and destroy them each... not
not to destroy... no they're rebuilding they're not literally... they're destroying it
in order to rebuild it. Every season? I don't think he means
every season, I think he means there was a time when they
needed to rebuild one, they did it in the other season. Okay
let's move on. Okay the גמרא says like this. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, גבו
זוזי ומחתי מאי, Gavu zuzay u-machtsify mai, let's say you actually collected
the money, you actually you made you have the money sitting in
the bank account, okay, can you then go ahead and build because
there's not a concern of פשיעותא pshiyuta in that case? If the
concern were פשיעותא, pshiyuta, it wouldn't be פשיעותא, pshiyuta, the money is
already collected. ומחתי machtsify is like you, like you, literally means like
to bring it down.
Okay, so you've collected the money and it's placed and it's ready
to be spent, what's the story? אמר ליה no, דלמא מיתרמי להו
פדיון שבויים ויהבי להו. dilma mitrami lehu pidyon shevuyim veyahavi lehu. So
no,
because you know, no, maybe at the last minute you'll decide you
have a better use for those funds. We need to redeem some
captives. That's not enough to ensure it's going to get done. שביזי
לבני והדרי הדרי ומחסי כשורא מאי. Shavizi livni vehadrei hadrei umachasei keshora
mai. Let's say you've got all of the bricks stacked up, all
of the roof shingles, all of the beams, okay, so all the
money, you know, all the building material is already there. Can I
now tear down the שול? shul? Obviously I'm going to build the
other one. אמר ליה no, זימנין דמיטרמי להו פדיון שבויים מזבני ויהבי
להו. zimnin demitrami lehu pidyon shevuyim mizabni veyahavi lehu. Sometimes it's an
opportunity to redeem captives
and then we're going to just sell all the building materials. Even
that's not enough to ensure it's going to get done. אי הכי
אפילו בנו נמי. Ee hachi afilu banu nami. So even after you
build it. Now this doesn't mean after you've built it before you
start using it. Once you use it, you can't pull down a
שול shul that's been in use. But maybe I would say you
can't even tear down the old one until you use the new
one. Right? Maybe even building it isn't enough. אמרי Amri no, דירסתיה
דאינשי לא מזבני. dirastya de-inshei lo mizabni. Once it's your once you
got a building you're not going to sell. I remember talking to
a contractor who said that David, you probably know about this. He
said that when they do things with שולס shuls they always like
up the fee like whatever it is twenty percent because you know
because
like invariably the project runs out of money in the middle. So
we said if the שול shul had actually put all of the
money in escrow ahead of time, just like then they would, you
know, then they wouldn't have to do that. Was that your experience,
David? Something similar.
Something okay anyway. ולא אמרן אלא דלא חזי בה תיוהא. Velo amran
ela delo chazi bei tyuva.
It's only if there has not been seen like rotting or something.
You know that there's not like this urgent need. If the current
one is actually rotting and you've got to address it right away.
וחזי בה תיוהא סתרי ובני. Vechazi bei tyuva satrei uvanai. In that
case you don't have to wait, you can tear it down and
we're more concerned with the שול shul falling apart than we are
with concerns about פשיעה peshiya or whatever. Now כי הא דרב אשי
ki ha derav ashi like the story of רב אשי Rav Ashi
חזא בתיוהא בבי כנישתא דמתא מחסיא chaza betyuva bevei knishta demata machasya
he saw that there was this rotting and people weren't dealing with
it at all. Okay so what did he do?
רש"י Rashi says I said rotting, רש"י Rashi says it means cracking,
but whatever the point means it's falling apart. Okay סתריה sasrei he
tore it down ועייליה לפורייה להתם veayilei lepuryei lehasam and he took
his cot there and he decided he's now sleeping on the grounds
of the שול shul until people do something to fix it up.
ולא אפקיה velo afkei he didn't take it out עד דתקינו ליה
שפיכי ad detakinu lei shefichi until they built the building together רש"י
Rashi says like with all of like the drainpipes, you know, until
they got it to be a good. Now could be that he
didn't tear down the whole building. Since it mentions drainpipes it could
be that they had a leaky roof, okay, and had to rebuild
the roof. So he tore down the roof, he put his bed
there, nobody wants him sitting in the middle of the rain, so
that was created an urgency to like build a roof and build
the gutters and do the drainpipes and that's how so which is
like a double message. On the one hand it's like we don't
worry about פשיעה peshiya if there's an urgent need that has to
get done if it's rotting if it's cracking. On the other hand,
he did worry about פשיעה peshiya because he felt that he had
to actually do something to make the people not negligent. He had
to actually start living there or else they were going to ignore
the problem even after he tore it down. So it's not totally
black and white. Even if you have an urgent need, the concern
about פשיעה peshiya is a non-negligent concern. Okay, תוספות Tosafot has a
whole other discussion also which is how are you allowed to sleep
in a שול shul and even after you've torn it down maybe
its status of a שול shul still remains. Okay so that raises
other interesting questions. We'll end here. Tomorrow it's going to transition from
this discussion to Herod's building of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So
we'll pick up with this tomorrow. Why don't we make קידוש Kiddush
in...